Privacy Commissioner coming in.
Okay.
Online.
Yeah.
Right. Right. So look, you're welcome to come to the table
now. Thank you. So then we'll hear from our petitioner.
Make it easier when we're replying.
Right. Do we have
Mr. Feldmann?
Ms.
Oh, sorry. Ms. Feldmann. So my apologies.
Yes, I'm here.
Yes. Right, so I'm Greg O'Connor, the chair of the committee.
We'll just get ourselves to introduce ourselves.
To my right, my-
I'm, so I'm Greg Fleming, the deputy chair of the committee.
I'm Andrew Bailey.
Kia ora, I'm Cindy Wade-Brown, Green List MP.
All right. So thank you. Now you can take your submission as read.
We have 10 minutes. Obviously, feel free to speak to it,
your points, but it would be good if you could leave time for questions.
We also have the officials from the Ministry of Justice at the
table. We'll be going to them afterwards
for their oversight. So welcome.
That's great. Thank you. Thank you for having the opportunity to speak
today.
As you know, my name is Katja Feldmann.
I'm a cybersecurity, governance, risk, and assurance professional
with over 13 years of experience working across
public and private sector organizations in New Zealand and
internationally.
The reason I launched this petition is simple.
As New Zealanders, we increasingly trust organizations with our most
sensitive information, yet the consequences for failing to protect
that information are often limited.
My petition is not about punishing organizations that experience
genuine cyber attacks, even if they take reasonable
precautions. It's more about ensuring that there are adequate
consequences where organizations fail to take reasonable steps
to protect personal information or repeatedly neglect their
privacy obligations.
All right. So that's
sums up-
Yeah
... nice summary. And
nothing else from -- Okay. Questions, members, then?
I've taken the submission as read.
I'm keen to get into the conversation with you.
What's the, yeah-
Yeah. Well, what we can do, so-
I did have a question.
Sorry.
Thank you, Katja.
Celia, questions.
You've listed the different penalties in different countries and
showing that we're
quite
minimal.
Have you seen evidence that those,
which sort of penalty at what sort of level actually makes the
difference in prevention? Because it's prevention we want,
not so much the slapping of the wrist afterwards.
That's right. Unfortunately, I guess once the penalties are apply,
you know, like if you were doing well in prevention, then you wouldn't get the
penalty in the first place. There is a website which, I
think it's called GDPR Tracker, that shows the different penalties
for different organizations, including private and public
sector. Sometimes you see a school, and then they get a very small penalty because
they're a school, they're obviously teachers and educational professionals,
so-
Wow
... it's quite a different
approach. So I think the smaller penalties
are probably good for encouraging
prevention and then the larger penalties when
repeatedly, and this is what we have seen, I think, with the Privacy
Commissioner, is where there repeatedly there are complaints, yet not much
is done to actually prevent further damages there.
Thank you.
Can I just, through you, Chair?
Yeah. Mr. Bailey.
Can I just ask a few questions?
I was the minister for stopping scams, so I sort of had
quite an interest in this.
So there's two sides to the coin, and I
wanted to understand your fundamental proposition before we jumped into the
penalties. But so of course, there's two sides.
One is we have a lot of personal scams
that occur because people are not good with
passwords or all that type of scams, right?
Yeah.
The other thing is what we did and what I started was we're putting in
place
arrangements between the banks,
then
the telcos, and then there has been agreement with the
Meta and the main digital providers.
Although that's probably more work to go in that field.
So
you're
talking about scams, but I presume you're not talking about the
personal, you're talking about
the large-scale
transfer of information, but it's occurred under
an illegal process, and you'll know where
most of these scams originate from
as much as I do.
So are you dealing with those industrial
leakages like we've had the, are you talking about the Hamilton Waikato
University?
How do you differentiate between all the other scams?
We lose billions of dollars a year from personal scams.
Sometimes,
misinformation
gets leaked but doesn't actually result in financial harm, might result in
emotional harm. So what I'm trying to understand for you is what your proposition
is.
I think essentially my proposition is probably having a look at
the Privacy Act as a whole and seeing how it
ties back to other legislation. Thinking like,
if you look at the Health and Safety Act, for example, before that was
tied to personal liability of directors of
companies. It also was not
always taken as seriously because- There's
sort of two layers to it. So if you look at,
I don't know if you've read recently, Booking.com had a big data breach, right?
So everyone that uses Booking.com, which is almost there's a lot of New
Zealanders, no doubt, that use it.
Booking.com failed to adequately protect
the information of their users, and then they get a
scam. So as the end user, like me opening that email, the
more organizations fail to protect that information,
and it leaks out to more different parties.
You just spread the attacks. We call it-
Okay
... sort of the attack surface. It just spreads.
So we're never going to get on top of scam if we keep leaking more and more-
Yeah
... of the information.
Okay, now I agree with sort of what you're trying to do.
But, so what you've said, just by inference from what you just said, is you don't
want to deal with personal scams, where someone
unwittingly
does something, right? You're talking about gross
misuse, transfer of data. Okay. So then there's
sort of components within that, because you'll be
aware through your own work that there's certain
organizations that get a high level of protection in New Zealand and are still
subject to massive attacks where big
data breaches. The hospital is one
area of that. You'll probably know what I'm talking about.
Yep.
And then large corporates,
once you get below,
I don't want to name companies, but
are not inside that boundary. So are you talking about
corporates here? Because your example was a corporate.
Or you're talking about government agencies?
Both. But obviously for government agents.
So it's not just about the penalties.
I think it's, as government agencies, they already have a security sort of
standard, which is the New Zealand Information-
They still get, they still-
... Security Manual.
But they still lose information.
Yeah, that's right. So I'm not sure if penalties would be the way to go because in
the end they, I guess, are just taxpayer money.
But so there maybe needs to be some
independent audits or something in that space.
But in the private sector, I think
penalties combined with some sort of
legal obligation to actually do
the... Because we're talking about prevention, right?
Ideally, we don't want anyone to pay that penalty.
Yeah.
Mm.
So there's two areas. Then you sort of get that down to two areas.
So one is what you, I think what you're saying there is
there'd be a general, sort of a bit like a Companies Act requirement, a
general requirement that if you possess people's personal details,
then you need to show reasonable efforts to make sure that's protected.
That's fine. If you're subject to a concerted attack by
one of the major players, and there's about four of them.
Even small firms,
I had a merchant bank, I lost some data at one stage.
We had good systems, right? We took all the precautions, but we still
lost data. And then the next point-
Well, just on that one. Under that, that's a good
example. So would, because they lost
data, in Mr. Bailey's example, would
that be almost a vicarious liability offense or
a liability offense because they lost it?
I think if that, talk if that-
Who would determine whether
the degree of care exercised
by Mr. Bailey's firm was adequate?
And that's I guess, another layer of this, because we have the
Privacy Act, but it's not very descriptive, right?
So somewhere there needs to be some standards that say, "These are the
minimum standards we expect organizations to follow."
Yeah.
And then if someone loses information, similar to what
happened at Manage My Health now, you can go in there and you can say, "Well,
legally you were supposed to follow this standard.
Here's all the stuff you did, here's all the stuff you didn't do." And then-
Okay. Now, Mr. Bailey, I think this is a good time actually to bring the officials
in-
Yeah. Can I just-
... who've heard this. Okay, one last question.
Yeah.
But we can come back to, Ms. Sheldon.
Just I think there's another
angle which I think you were getting at as well,
and this is what we tried to do with the banks and the telcos, and ultimately
the measure of stuff is the sharing of knowledge.
So if you have been
attacked,
the agreement that there is with the banks, for instance, is that
they have to share that data, and they can share data
simultaneously without being legally
liable. So it's almost making sure that there is a network
there that means that they can be protected,
and more readily therefore, more readily the key actors in the
market, because most scams come through those three sources,
are then stopped in their tracks much earlier than otherwise.
So sharing data to stop the-
Yeah
... to, kind of-
And that's a crucial bit-
Or, well, look-
A crucial part of it
... okay, look, well, this, you've heard this, why it's useful to have you
here. I'll just now invite
our Ministry of Justice officials to take us away.
Kia ora koutou. Thank you for inviting us to speak with the committee.
So the Ministry of Justice provided a written submission on the petition in
April
of this year, and in summary, that submission
provided an overview of the current enforcement settings in the Privacy Act and the
powers available to the Privacy Commissioner.
It noted the concerns of the petitioner's submission with the current
enforcement and penalty settings in the Act, and also
mentioned that we are developing advice on
options to incentivize the protection of personal information
as part of-
The National Cybersecurity Action Plan 2026 to
2027.
So if there are no specific questions on what we provided in our written
submission, I can just talk through the points we made in that submission.
Do you want to-
Or do you... No, you can...
No, no. You should talk to-
Yeah, no. So carry on
All right. So, in terms of the Privacy Act, it came into effect on
1 December 2020. Its purpose is to protect and promote
people's right to privacy over their personal information.
It applies to individuals and agencies.
And when we say agencies, we mean
agencies that decide to collect personal information for a particular
purpose. And the Privacy Commissioner is an independent Crown
entity, and he has a range of powers under the act,
including resolving complaints and enforcing compliance.
The act is principles based rather than rules based.
And the principles are intended to be flexible and proportionate,
both to the range of agencies or organizations the act applies to,
and based on the nature of the information they hold.
So the act is quite context specific.
In terms of the commissioner's role,
the commissioner has a role in terms of resolving individual complaints.
So any person can make a complaint alleging that
an action of an agency is an interference with their privacy,
and then the commissioner will decide whether or not to investigate that
complaint. And the complaint may lead to a settlement
between the complainant and the agency, an assurance
from the agency that the action will not be repeated.
The commissioner could investigate the complaint.
The commissioner can make a referral to the Director of Human Rights,
Review Tribunal proceedings.
And the tribunal, the Human Rights Review Tribunal, may award
remedies to an individual if satisfied that there has been a
privacy interference,
including damages up to a maximum of $350,000.
Then there are
enforcement powers available to the commissioner.
So I've just talked about the individual complaints that they
deal with. But in terms of the enforcement powers of the commissioner, they can
inquire into any matter that appears to be an infringement with the privacy
of individuals,
can investigate a complaint or a matter about which a complaint may be made
under the act. They can issue compliance notices to agencies if they
consider the agency has breached the act, a privacy
principle, or a relevant code of practice.
And the compliance notice
can sets out the nature of the breach, and then it can direct agencies
to take specific steps to remedy the breach.
And compliance notices are enforceable through the Human Rights Review Tribunal.
And failure to comply with the tribunal is an
offense. It's a criminal offense punishable by a fine of up to
$10,000.
And then there are various other criminal offenses under the act, also punishable
by a fine of up to $10,000 on conviction.
In terms of the
effectiveness of existing penalties and enforcement tools,
the petitioner is correct to say that New Zealand is becoming
somewhat of an outlier compared to privacy and regulatory
settings internationally. Other jurisdictions certainly have
strengthened
regulatory powers in recent years.
So Australia, the EU, and the UK, they have
introduced civil penalties for breaches of their privacy legislation,
and the fines are in the millions. Australia, I think, most recently has gone up to
40 million.
Mm-hmm.
New Zealand's privacy law does not have civil penalties.
And this is really because the act is
based on an individual complaints model, and it's ensuring the commissioner can
resolve complaints rather than enforce compliance.
So the recommendations in the petition that the act introduce a stronger penalty
regime,
for serious or repeated privacy breaches,
are similar to what the privacy commissioner has called for in the past.
Mm-hmm.
In terms of our current work,
we're working on advice on options to
incentivize the protection of personal information, which could look at
introducing penalties into the Privacy Act.
So-
Are there any questions?
Sorry. So it's work you're doing-
Yes
... under the auspices of the-
The Cybersecurity Action Plan.
Right.
Okay. And will
some of these recommendations...
I mean,
what are the terms of reference essentially for that?
Is it pretty wide-ranging to actually
re-
In terms of the recommendation?
Yeah.
It's to-
Or the terms of reference-
... provide advice on options to
incentivize the protection of personal information,
including, for example,
introducing civil penalties.
Right. When will you provide that advice?
When?
Yeah.
Soon.
Yes.
And when do you reckon the cyber plan's going to be introduced?
Well, the minister will make decisions, the Minister of Justice, in due course.
Right.
So imminent.
So-
It's subject to, yeah, the minister-
Then your advice is imminent going to the Minister of Justice.
Shortly.
Shortly. Very good.
So let's just say these...
Okay, so who's got the investigative team?
Who has the ability to investigate these breaches?
The Privacy Commissioner.
Commissioner.
They currently have the ability to investigate.
Okay. And does he have the ability, or she, do they have the ability
to do this? What sort of Because this is we-
To investigate?
One, no. I think the
Privacy Commissioner's clearly got the ability to investigate.
Yeah.
I think the question is does he have the capability?
And secondly, my second question would be, has he undertaken any
investigations in recent times? So is that a latent power or is
it a power that's used actively?
Well, he most recently inquired into the Manage My Health data breach.
Did anyone get fined, killed, taken to jail,
locked up?
Well, there were findings made in relation to that.
So he found that both Manage My Health
and Health New Zealand
failed in their responsibilities to-
But they opened the door, didn't they?
That's correct, and both breached rule five of-
And did they get a penalty though?
Well, no, because the commissioner does not have the ability to-
How do you, and this is what the petitioner started asking,
if you were to put a stronger regime in, who would prosecute in the case
of the Waikato Hospital we talked about?
Who would take it, and who would be sued? Is it the board?
Is it the managing director, or is it the
CTO?
And who would take that case?
Who would take the case?
Yeah, to sue them.
One of the options is that the case would be taken by the
commissioner-
Mm
... but in the end it would be a court, the High Court-
Yeah, but have you got funding for it?
... potentially that would decide.
Have you got funding for it?
Someone's got to put this, this to top my question, someone's got to put this.
These are going to be massive cases, particularly against some of these big
corporates.
And it's hard to think that a couple of ex-cops working for the
have got that capability to do it.
And particularly once these fines get up around, if
the recommendations that the sanctions become much greater.
But it would be done under the auspices of the Privacy Commissioner.
Correct.
Okay. I think we
might have a talk afterwards about that.
Yeah.
There's the Privacy Commissioner now.
Good. Well, actually, let's bring the Privacy Commissioner on right now.
Good timing.
Because we didn't know you were there. He was hidden. Secret agents.
Thank you.
Afternoon, Mr. Chair, members.
Good. Well, you've sat there, you've managed to hear the
petitioner and ministry, so you can
join all the bits up for us. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Chair, and I'm joined today by Ed Kennedy and Ushana
Jayasuriya from my office, from the policy team.
Very briefly, as the submitter has noted, and as you will be aware,
my office continues to see serious privacy breaches
happening. As has just been referred to, most recently,
the Manage My Health inquiry. We have formally reported on
phase one of the inquiry, and our
finding that they had
breached what is known as Rule 5 of the Health Information Privacy
Code has led to us saying
publicly that we will issue
compliance notices to them. Which is a tool available in our regulatory
toolbox to direct them to take certain action or to stop doing certain
things to ensure that they come back within their
operations within the ambit of the requirements of the Privacy Act.
That, at the moment, is the most significant tool in many ways in our
regulatory toolbox.
Given that this is a petition, Mr. Chair, I thought members might be interested to
know a little bit about what we're hearing from members of the public.
We've just conducted our 2026
privacy survey, which shows that concerns about
privacy in general are deepening and diversifying.
Not only are more people concerned about their individual privacy than ever
before, but a greater number are saying that in the last few
years they've become more and more concerned, which I think is a reflection
of the significant cyber attacks and data privacy breaches we've
seen over recent years.
Our survey actually asked questions around the matter that is part of the
topic of the petition today, and New Zealanders continue to support the
need for greater enforcement powers under the Act, with support
from over 70% of the respondents.
Of those, 75% of those respondents wanted to see higher penalties,
and 74% supported audit powers, something else referred to by
the petitioner. So there is a strong degree
of public interest and support for what
I would describe as adding another tool to the regulatory
toolbox of this office. A financial penalty regime
is one tool
in the compliance enforcement toolbox.
It's an important tool, and it's a missing tool.
We do actually regulate along a spectrum.
For agencies that are trying to do privacy well, we might encourage,
educate, provide guidance, provide warnings, those sorts
of ends of the regulatory spectrum.
But at the other end, Mr. Chair, members, where we see poor or
deliberate mismanagement of people's personal information, we
believe that's where we need to have a stronger set of tools
available to us. We have the compliance notice approach, as I've
outlined, but also the ability, like my colleagues in other
countries, to seek financial penalties through the court system
or indeed to even issue infringement fines for lower level breaches
of privacy is something that we believe
is something that is needed in our operations.
I guess in many ways, though, our
focus is also on building what I'd describe as the
privacy fence at the top of the cliff, rather than always being the privacy
ambulance at the bottom dealing with- These extraordinary large data
privacy breaches and complaints from individuals about
interference with their privacy.
So as part of a legislative reform package, we
would also, and have in the past, advocated for things
like audit powers for the office,
for agencies like public and private sector organizations to
be subject to accountability principles that require them to be
more transparent, I guess, about what they're doing to ensure
that they both protect and respect individuals' personal
information.
But as the committee will know and has heard,
the office of the Ministry of Justice is responsible for privacy
policy. We're very much the regulator in this space.
It is up to the Ministry and the government of the day to decide
whether they wish to advance reform along these lines.
We're very supportive of the direction of reform in terms of a
financial penalty power for this office.
We would exercise that carefully.
I can talk, if the committee wishes, about the sort of thing we might be talking
about,
and perhaps in comparison terms that some members will be familiar with,
if you're interested, Mr. Chair. For example, if you think about the Commerce
Commission in relation to the Fair Trading Act, they have a
similar financial penalty regime.
So probably looking at a financial penalty regime
consistent with consumer law, that sort of thing.
Officials, of course, have a better understanding of the nature of the different
financial penalty regimes that apply across different regulatory areas.
But we're not looking for something extraordinary.
We're looking for something that would allow us to send a strong
signal for the most egregious and poor management of
people's personal information. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Thank you. Just a question. Say, the Waikato Hospital breach.
There's presumably an inquiry into the breaches, into
the hackers.
That's done
currently by police.
Yeah.
So there's that inquiry as to the criminals who have gone
in and stolen the information.
That's-
And number-
That's separate to any inquiry regarding the
privacy issue, presumably. Is that it?
That's right. If criminal action activity has taken place, for example,
hackers are breaking into, the most recent case, ManageMyHealth,
that is something for the police to consider looking
at. But under our current privacy law,
if you suffer what is defined as a serious privacy breach,
you have to, by law, report that to my office, and we have the ability to assess
that and, if we wish, to investigate that to see what happened and
why, and whether appropriate and reasonable steps were taken
in terms of the requirements you need to meet to protect personal
information in Privacy Act, to see whether those requirements were in fact
actually met.
So do you work -- well, presumably there is a criminal inquiry into
ManageMyHealth.
So will you be working with the police on that?
I'm not sure if there is actually going on at the moment in that
area. We have completed our report into phase one, which
found that both ManageMyHealth and Health New
Zealand failed to have in place reasonable security
safeguards to protect individuals' personal information.
So from my perspective, they failed to meet the requirements of the
Privacy Act, which is why we're taking further regulatory action in response to
that.
The actual identification of the hackers
is not something that we would necessarily be interested in, and that would be a
matter for
police. But we understand that actually identifying
who those hackers might be and then holding them to account is in itself a
very challenging
thing to do.
Well, you'd need to find out how they got in, though, wouldn't you?
Because that's going to be very much part of if you're going to take a case against
ManageMyHealth, then part of the
actus reus is going to be finding out how the people got in.
So I'm just surprised you wouldn't be working more closely with them.
Well, as part of our inquiry, Mr. Chair, we actually brought in
specialist forensic IT support to assist my team
here, and they were able to help us identify
the failures in security from the agency concerned
and to identify what hardening and strengthening of systems now needs
to happen. So we brought that in ourselves.
As Eva said, I think we know it was the hacker group Kazoo, I think they
were called.
Mm-hmm.
These are often based in countries a long way away from here,
Mr. O'Connor, and
kind of difficult and beyond the reach of our authorities.
But the privacy failure, if proved, is something that we very
much can and do have a say and have a look at.
We want to make sure they're not in Te Awamutu though, don't we?
Mr. Bailey.
Yeah. Can I just ask a couple questions? One is jurisdiction.
You can
require any entity, whether private or government entity, that
every entity is subject to Privacy Act?
That's right. It's an extraordinarily broad remit, so all public and private
sector entities from the large corporate to the corner store, non-governmental
organizations, all those sorts of groups.
Okay. And in terms of actions,
have you taken anyone to court?
Not in my time as Privacy Commissioner, and I don't think so before then, no.
I don't believe we've ever prosecuted anyone.
But that begs the question-
Mm
... even if you increase the penalties-
... why haven't you? And I presume one of a significant issue in
terms of funding of your office, capability, expense of
taking court cases to the High Court.
Can you say why you haven't taken any cases?
Sure. We've operated to date on the basis of the
current tools available to us, and the most
commonly used and powerful one for us is the compliance notice.
So we don't need to go down the court route.
Prosecutions under our act are normally in relation
to a failure to follow, for example, the requirements of a
compliance notice. So it's failure to follow lawfully the requirements
imposed on an agency by this office.
If we-
So you basically have to go through a two-step.
Yeah.
One is to issue the notice. If they don't do anything, then you
have to... But what happens if there's gross negligence?
Yeah.
Because it's different cases, and I don't know whether you heard me talking before,
but
we've got an orchestrated actor, and there's many
well-known actors are doing it.
And that's a national level.
Even if you have a very good system, then a lot of people will be
subject. Even the American
major institutions have been hacked.
So there's an issue of graduation-
Yeah
... but then there's a system of where there's a gross,
let's say Hamilton, on the primary facie, where it was a gross
case of
doing silly stuff, right? Negligence.
Presumably, you'd also want the power to be able to take them straight to court
for an appropriate, rather than just go through this graduated
process. Or is that not your preference?
Yes. Absolutely. So what I was
saying was if we had a financial penalty regime
specified in the Privacy Act,
what we would do would be, having assessed the nature of a breach, the reasons for
it, if it was due to deliberate or
incredibly poor management by the agency's governance and
leadership concerned, we may well decide to go down the financial
penalty regime and seek a financial penalty through the court system.
And you're absolutely right, Mr. Bayly.
We would then need to have the ability to fund such court action. Yes.
So really what we're hearing is Ms.
Feldman is right, that there is, currently,
we really are without a regime that's going to give
meaningful
sanction
and to organizations which
don't adequately protect the information they have, the personal
information they have. Would that be fair from your point of view?
Absolutely, Mr. Chair.
A financial penalty regime immediately sharpens
that sense of accountability around the boardroom table.
It provides a demonstration effect to other actors in that area as well.
If they can see one of their colleagues in whatever sector of activity
that's going on, let's say it's the health sector or the banking sector.
If they see someone being hit with a large fine, it'll make everybody
sit up and pay attention. It makes the board of directors turn to the chief
executive and say, "What kind of work are you doing to harden, for
example, your IT systems?" So it has a positive effect beyond the
agency concerned.
So presumably, this conversation has taken place elsewhere, that
Ms. Feldman's not the only person who's been concerned about
this.
No, I have been talking about it since I took up this role four years ago.
I've been speaking to my colleagues in other countries about what they're doing in
this space. We're seeing a greater degree of
using this tool coming through from our Australian colleagues, for example.
And as you've heard from the Ministry of Justice, this is something that they're
looking at as well and has indeed been put forward as something that
needs some serious thought as part of the government of the day's
cybersecurity action plan, as you've heard.
Well, I'd say that we're yet as a committee to meet and discuss that,
but it may well be that that will be our own conclusion from what we've
heard today. Members, are there any other questions-
There was one other dimension
... of any of our officials or in fact even our
petitioner?
Commissioner, I don't know whether you heard before, but
the other element is
you talked about prevention, and there is a prevention.
If there is a breach, let's say of
number of organizations. As the minister put that thing
in place with the banks, it's now been rolled out with telecom and
the other internet providers. But
one of the key components of that was to be able to share when they were aware of
attacks,
particularly in the relation to scams.
The way you framed it, if someone has
got a breach of data, they've got to send it to you.
First of all, do you share that data immediately with the relevant people to say,
"We're aware of this"?
Or you don't get that in real time, so by the time you get it, it's too late?
Or do you allow those organizations make
other people aware of what's happening, and there's a mechanism to do that really
quickly? Because that's in the best interests of New Zealand, not just an
organization.
Sure. A couple of things on that, and I'll ask my colleague to talk as well.
Breach reporting to us is treated with a high degree of confidentiality,
because the fact that there has been a breach for a particular organization
may actually be even market sensitive, and so they need to be careful about
how they message that and plan for that.
Second, in my time in the role, I've had a number of meetings, for example, with
the banking ombudsman, with the Bankers Association, with banks to
discuss that very issue, to ensure that they have
the freedom to share information in a way that,
while respecting people's privacy, allows the goal of protecting
individuals' financial
stewardship to be protected as well. Eve, anything further?
Yeah. On that point, my team has been involved in the
Anti-Scam Alliance work, so the collaboration pillar for the Anti-Scam Alliance
about information sharing to-
prevent and detect scams. The other point I'd note is just that the
commissioner has powers under the act to
refer matters on to other agencies where appropriate, if it's
an issue that's better placed resolved by another
regulatory agency, for example. So we have information sharing powers to give
effect to that under our act already as well.
And one other question. If an organization is
hacked,
and the blackmail, what's the word, that they're blackmailed to-
Yeah
... give the information back, and they do that, and they don't
report to their customers
that that information was hacked.
Do you deal with that? Is it an offense to do that?
Yeah. It's a breach of the Privacy Act to not report a, what we
would regard as a serious breach.
And so what we do see, Mr. Chair, is organizations reporting breaches
to us that might not be serious because people from abundance of
caution are now getting into the habit of doing that.
The sorts of organizations that would be reluctant to report a
breach are the sorts of organizations that we would have the greatest degree of
concern about, and probably would be looking at to hit with a financial penalty
if we found that they had been poor stewards of the personal information that they
had available to them. Absolutely.
All right. And just finally, so we're going to have to keep moving, but-
Yeah
... we've
had the justice officials, we've had a very well-informed
petitioner, and yourselves.
The Petitions Committee will be looking to report on this.
Is there anyone else that you would suggest we should be talking to or hearing from
here that would be able to enlighten us a little further about this from the
top of your head? Or even if you were to afterwards think of
anyone, we'd be quite here because
we see this as a search for
an answer, and making sure we have all the facts available.
So if any other petitioners actually, or any of our submitters,
thought there was anyone else, any industry bodies that might be
worth talking to?
Certainly. Even a quick Google search of financial penalties
privacy will throw up a number of both
NGO expert privacy consultancy
law firm commentators talking about
the value of a financial penalty regime in this space.
As
I said, as part of a regulatory toolkit.
One tool, an important tool, but remembering that there are others as well.
All right. Any other pressing questions, members? All right.
And back to our
petitioner. Thank you very much.
I would like to think what we exist for, to make sure
that someone like yourself with that knowledge can bring it forward, and
hopefully we can report and either,
if not get things moving,
lubricate the wheels.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Make sure-
Thank you
... things are already happening.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you. Bye.